So now let's do a summary
Giờ hãy tổng kết
of Amazon S3 from a database perspective.
về Amazon S3 dưới góc nhìn cơ sở dữ liệu.
So, S3 is a key value store for objects.
S3 là kho key-value cho các object.
And it's great when you want to store big objects,
Rất phù hợp khi bạn muốn lưu object lớn,
it's not great to store many small objects.
nhưng không tốt để lưu nhiều object nhỏ.
So Amazon S3 is serverless,
Amazon S3 là serverless,
you have infinite scaling.
bạn có khả năng mở rộng vô hạn.
The maximum object size is five terabytes
Kích thước object tối đa là 5 terabyte
and you can version objects over time.
và bạn có thể version object theo thời gian.
You have different storage tiers,
Bạn có nhiều lớp lưu trữ khác nhau,
so you have S3 Standard, Infrequent Access, Intelligent
như S3 Standard, Infrequent Access, Intelligent,
and you have a Glacier,
và Glacier,
and if you want to transition between the tiers
và nếu muốn chuyển giữa các lớp
you can use lifecycle policies.
bạn có thể dùng lifecycle policy.
Some important features you need to know
Một số tính năng quan trọng cần biết
about are versioning, encryption, replication,
gồm versioning, encryption, replication,
multifactor authentication deletes, MFA deletes,
MFA delete
and access logs.
và access log.
In terms of security, you have IAM security
Về bảo mật, bạn có IAM
but you can also have bucket policies
và có thể dùng bucket policy
on top of your S3 buckets.
cho bucket S3.
You have ACL, you have Access Points for Amazon S3.
Bạn có ACL và Access Points cho Amazon S3.
Then you have S3 object Lambda to modify objects
Có S3 Object Lambda để chỉnh sửa object
before they are sent to the applications.
trước khi gửi đến ứng dụng.
You have CORS, and you have the concept
Có CORS và khái niệm
of Object Lock or Vault Lock for Glacier, which you know-
Object Lock hay Vault Lock cho Glacier,
which you need to know about in depth.
bạn cần hiểu sâu.
In terms of encryption mechanisms, we have different ones.
Về cơ chế mã hóa, có nhiều lựa chọn.
We have SSE-S3,
Có SSE-S3,
SSE-KMS where you can bring your own KMS key.
SSE-KMS dùng khóa KMS của bạn.
You have SSE-C, you can do client site encryption.
Có SSE-C và mã hóa phía client.
You have encryption TLS encryption in transit
Có mã hóa TLS khi truyền,
and you can set a default encryption scheme
và bạn có thể đặt mã hóa mặc định
for your S3 buckets.
cho bucket S3.
And if you wanted to operate on all the files in
Nếu muốn thao tác trên toàn bộ file
Amazon S3 buckets at a time you can use S3 batch
trong bucket S3, bạn dùng S3 Batch
to do batch operations, and this is very helpful,
để thực hiện các thao tác hàng loạt, rất hữu ích
for example, when you want to encrypt unencrypted objects
khi bạn muốn mã hóa các object chưa mã hóa
on an existing Amazon S3 buckets,
trong bucket hiện có,
or when you want to copy existing files
hoặc khi muốn sao chép file sẵn có
from one bucket to another before enabling S3 replication.
từ bucket này sang bucket khác trước khi bật replication.
And to create this list of files,
Để tạo danh sách file này
you can use S3 inventory, for example.
bạn có thể dùng S3 Inventory.
In terms of performance improvements
Về cải thiện hiệu năng
on Amazon S3, you can use multi-part upload
trên S3, bạn có thể dùng multipart upload
to upload files in, in a parallel way.
để tải tệp song song.
You can have S3 transfer
Bạn có S3 Transfer
acceleration to transfer S3 files faster
Acceleration để truyền file nhanh hơn
from one region to another region
giữa các vùng,
and S3 select to only retrieve the data you need
và S3 Select để chỉ lấy dữ liệu cần
out of Amazon S3.
từ S3.
For automation, you can use S3 event notifications
Để tự động hóa, bạn dùng S3 Event Notifications
that has interfaces with SNS, SQS, Lambda, and EventBridge.
kết hợp với SNS, SQS, Lambda và EventBridge.
And this allows you to, for example,
Điều này cho phép bạn, ví dụ,
react to events where new objects are created
phản ứng khi có object mới
on your Amazon S3 buckets.
trong bucket S3.
So the use cases for Amazon S3 are around static files.
Các trường hợp dùng S3 là lưu trữ file tĩnh.
It's going to be a key value store
Nó là kho key-value
for huge files or website hosting.
cho file lớn hoặc host website.
So hopefully I'm not teaching you anything new here,
Hy vọng tôi không dạy bạn điều gì mới,
and if you have any doubts on any
nếu còn thắc mắc
of these features, and they can all appear at the exam
về các tính năng này và chúng có thể xuất hiện trong kỳ thi,
then I would suggest you go back to the Amazon S3 section.
hãy quay lại phần Amazon S3.
Okay.
Được rồi.
That's it.
Hết rồi.
I hope you liked it.
Hy vọng bạn thích.
And I will see you in the next lecture.
Hẹn gặp ở bài tiếp theo.